Arna Bontemps Papers
Arna Bontemps Papers
- Writings
  - Articles and essays
    - Introductions
      - Hold Fast to Dreams, See "On Integrating the Old with the New".
      - "Negro Poetry for Young People" (Folkways FC7114), typescript manuscripts (Box 32)
      - Not Without Laughter / by Langston Hughes, typescript manuscript (Box 32)
      - 100 Years of Negro Freedom / by Arna Bontemps, typescript manuscripts; photocopy from New York: Dodd, Mead & Company, 1961 edition (Box 32)
      - The Poetry of the Negro "revised" / edited by Arna Bontemps and Langston Hughes, holograph; typescript manuscripts (Box 32)
      - Unidentified work by or about Scott Joplin, holograph and typescript manuscripts (Box 32)
    - "Is the Colored Press Necessary?"' unidentified newspaper, "Afro-Magazine Section", Feb. 9, 1957 (Box 32)
    - "The James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters," The Yale University Library Gazette, Oct. 1943 (Box 32)
    - "The Jubilee Singers of Fisk University", typescript manuscripts (Box 32)
    - "Langston Hughes", typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Line,"The Saturday Review, Aug. 22, 1953 (Box 33)
    - "Literature for Intercultural Education," Arts in Childhood, Series III, Bulletin 2; The Ispescope, Vol. 1, no. 4, 1948; typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Lonesome Boy Theme," The Horn Book Magazine, Dec. 1966; typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Low-Down on TB," National Tuberculosis Association, circa 1941 (Box 33)
    - "Maker of Demons," The Message Magazine, Sept. 1949; typescript manuscript (Box 33)
    - "My dear young friends... ", typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Negro Awakening: What Librarians Can Do," Library Journal, Sept. 1, 1963; typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Negro Contribution to American Letters", typescript manuscripts; photocopy of selection from The Black American Reference Book (1976) reprinted from The American Negro Reference Book (1966), edited by J. P. Davis; 3 folders (Box 33)
    - "Negro Culture", typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Negro in White America: Cultural Status", typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "Negro Newspapers", Feb. 9, 1943; memorandum to Ralph A. Beals, University of Chicago Libraries (Box 33)
    - "Negro Poetry in the United States", typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "Negro Poets in the U. S. A." for Folkway Records anthology (FP91/2), typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "Negro Poets, Then and Now" - Phylon, Vol. XI, no. 4, typescript manuscripts (Box 33)
    - "The Negro Renaissance: Jean Toomer and the Harlem Writers of the 1920's", research notes; typescript manuscripts (2 folders); photocopy of selection from Anger, and Beyond, edited by Herbert Hill (New York: Harper & Row, circa 1966) (Box 33)
    - "The Negro Writer," The Peabody Reflector, Jan. 1953; typescript manuscript (Box 34)
    - "Negro Writers," Northwestern University On the Air, Nov. 18, 1941; transcript of radio conversation (Box 34)
    - "Negro Writers in Chicago," The Chicago Sun Bee, undated (Box 34)
    - "The New Black Renaissance," Negro Digest, Nov. 1961; typescript manuscripts; 2 folders (Box 34)
    - New Standard Encyclopedia entry for "Civil Rights Movement", photocopy (Box 34)
    - "On Integrating the Old with the New", typescript manuscripts; photocopy of Introduction for Hold Fast to Dreams (Chicago: Follett, 1969) (Box 34)
    - "Only Half a Life" (Evanston, Ill.: National WCTU Publishing House, 1947) (Box 34)
    - "A Pianist with a Mind of Her Own: Hazel Scott," Senior Scholastic, Mar. 5, 1945 (Box 34)
    - "The Private Library and Personal Papers of W. E. B. Du Bois, typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Race Relations," Northwestern University On the Air, May 27, 1944; transcript of radio conversation; typescript (Box 34)
    - "Ralph J. Bunche", typescripts (Box 34)
    - "Rare and Fine Books" by Bibliophilus, newspaper column in The Chicago Sun, 1942-1943; undated (Box 34)
    - "Reflections on Richard Wright: a Symposium on an Exiled Native Son", typescript manuscripts of Bontemps' contribution to 1964 Asilomar Conference discussion; photocopy of selection from Anger, and Beyond, edited by Herbert Hill (New York: Harper & Row, circa 1966) (Box 34)
    - "Remembering Cane", holograph, typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Report to Opportunity Fellowships Committee", typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "A Response to Long Black Song: Essays in the Black American Literary Tradition / by Houston Baker, Jr., typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Richard Wright", typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Rock, Church, Rock!", typescript manuscript (Box 34)
    - "Rolf Italiaander at Fisk", typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Sad-Faced Author," The Horn Book Magazine, Jan./Feb. 1939; typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Saturday Night: Portrait of a Small Southern Town, 1938", typescript manuscript (Box 34)
    - "The Secrets of Booker T. Washington" (a synopsis for an article), typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Sing a Soothing Song," Top of the News, Mar. 1959; typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Six Voices" for Folkways Records "Anthology of Negro Poets" (FP91/1), typescript manuscript (Box 34)
    - "The Slave Narrative: an American Genre" (from Great Slave Narratives), typescript manuscripts (Box 34)
    - "Special Collections of Negroana" - The Library Quarterly, July 1944; typescript manuscripts; 4 folders (Box 34)
    - "Spirituals", typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "Story of the Negro," The Afro-American, 1949 (serialized); Negro Digest, July 1948 (excerpt) (Box 35)
    - "The Talented Tenth," Negro Digest, Dec. 1947 (Box 35)
    - "The Task of the Negro Writer as Artist: 'Statement by Arna Bontemps'," Negro Digest, Apr. 1965; holograph and typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "They Seek a City" (excerpt), Negro Digest, Aug. 1945 (Box 35)
    - "3 Pennies for Luck," Chicago Tribune Books Today, Dec. 4, 1966; typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
      See also Writings: Stories.
    - "Three Portraits of the Negro," The Saturday Review, Mar. 28, 1953 (Box 35)
    - "Three Visitors to Tennessee," Tennessee Librarian, June 1955; typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "The Tradition of Black Poetry", typescript manuscript (Box 35)
    - "A Tribute to Du Bois" - Negro Digest, July 1964; Journal of Human Relations, 1966, 1st, typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "The Two Harlems," American Scholar, Spring 1945; typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "The University Library", typescript manuscript (Box 35)
    - "Versions of the Bible" (working title: "The Good Book"), The Message Magazine, Nov. 1953; typescript manuscripts (Box 35)
    - "White Haitians", typescript manuscripts (Box 36)
    - "White Southern Friends of the Negro" (working title: "Southern White Friends of the Negro"), typescript manuscripts (Box 36)
    - "Why I Returned" (working title: "Why I Stayed"), typescript manuscripts; photocopy of selection from The South Today, edited by Willie Morris (New York: Harper & Row, 1965); 2 folders (Box 36)
    - "William Still and the Underground Railroad," The Message Magazine, June 1945 (Box 36)
    - "Words Like Freedom," The Journal (Louisiana Education Association), Jan. 1966; PLA Bulletin, Nov. 1966, typescript manuscripts (Box 36)
    - "Young Ben of West Point," Negro Digest, Apr. 1945 (Box 36)
    - [Untitled] (Box 36)
    - Essay-review on the Negro and children's literature for the New York Herald Tribune, 1965 (Box 36)
      Fisk University library
      Harassment of Langston Hughes, Oct. 15, 1963
      1958-59 musical season at Fisk University
      Text for pamphlet for Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc.
  - Book reviews (by title)
    - A- N, 9 folders (Box 36)
    - O-Z, 4 folders (Box 37)
  - Books
    - American Negro Poetry [anthology] (Box 37, 38)
      Research notes
      Contributors' manuscripts
      Biographical notes, rights and permissions
      Front matter, Introduction - manuscript
      Typescript manuscript - setting copy (2 folders)
      Index
      Galleys
    - Anyplace But Here [with Jack Conroy, revised and expanded version of They Seek a City] (Box 38, 39)
      Research notes (2 folders)
      Typescript manuscript (4 folders)
      Typescript manuscript - setting copy
    - Black Thunder [novel] (Box 39)
      Holograph manuscript (5 notebooks in 2 folders)
      Later revision titled "Gabriel's Attempt" (unfinished)
    - The Book of Negro Folklore [anthology, edited with Langston Hughes] (Box 39, 40, 41)
      Typescript manuscript (6 folders)
      Galleys (2 folders)
    - Bubber Goes to Heaven (working title: "Bubber Joins the Band") [juvenile], typescript manuscript (Box 41)
    - Chariot in the Sky [novel], typescript manuscripts (Box 41, 42)
    - Drums at Dusk (working titles: "The Scourge"; "Troubled Island") [novel], typescript, miscellaneous pages (Box 42)
    - Famous Negro Athletes [juvenile] (Box 43)
      Research material (5 folders)
      Typescript manuscript (3 folders)
    - The Fast Sooner Hound [juvenile, with Jack Conroy], typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 43)
    - Frederick Douglass: Slave, Fighter, Freeman [juvenile] (Box 43, 44)
      Typescript manuscripts (4 folders)
    - Free at Last: the Life of Frederick Douglass [juvenile] (Box 44, 45)
      See also Writings: Books: 100 Years of Negro Freedom; Writings: Miscellaneous: "The Free and the Fatherless": Frederick Douglass section.
      Typescript manuscripts (5 folders)
      Galleys (3 folders)
    - George Washington Carver (working title: "Carver's Green Thumb") [juvenile] (Box 45)
      Typescript manuscripts
    - Great Slave Narratives [anthology] (Box 45, 46, 47)
      Introduction and notes
      Research material (4 folders)
      Manuscript - setting copy (6 folders)
    - The Harlem Renaissance Remembered: Essays (Box 47, 48, 49)
      Manuscript submissions, A-Z by author (4 folders)
      Galleys (4 folders)
    - Hold Fast to Dreams: Poems Old and New [anthology] (Box 49, 50)
      Manuscripts (miscellaneous)
      Miscellany, chiefly publication fee records for contributors
    - Lonesome Boy [juvenile] (Box 50)
      Typescript manuscripts (2 folders)
      Page proofs
    - Mr. Kelso's Lion [juvenile], typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 50)
    - The Old South: "A Summer Tragedy" and Other Stories of the Thirties, typescript manuscripts; galleys; 4 folders (Box 50)
    - 100 Years of Negro Freedom, research notes; typescript manuscripts; 8 folders (Box 51)
      see also Writings: Miscellaneous: "The Free and the Fatherless".
    - The Pasteboard Bandit [juvenile], typescript manuscript (Box 51)
    - Personals [poetry], page proofs (Box 51)
    - The Poetry of the Negro [anthology, with Langston Hughes] (Box 52, 53, 54)
      Correspondence with contributors (2 folders)
      Biographical material of contributors
      Notes (2 folders)
      Typescript manuscripts (15 folders)
    - Sam Patch, the High, Wide, & Handsome Jumper [juvenile, with Jack Conroy], research notes; typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Slappy Hooper, the Wonderful Sign Painter [juvenile, with Jack Conroy] (Box 54)
      Typescript manuscripts (3 folders)
    - The Story of George Washington Carver [juvenile] (Box 54, 55)
      Chapter outline
      Suggestions for re-write
      Typescript manuscripts (6 folders)
    - Story of the Negro (Box 55, 56)
      Research notes (4 folders)
    - They Seek a City [with Jack Conroy, revised and expanded as Anyplace But Here], research notes; typescript manuscripts; 7 folders (Box 56)
    - We Have Tomorrow, typescript manuscripts, miscellaneous (Box 57)
    - Young Booker: Booker T. Washington's Early Days [juvenile] (Box 57, 58)
      See also Writings: Books: 100 Years of Negro Freedom; Writings: Miscellaneous: "The Free and the Fatherless": Booker T. Washington section.
      Manuscript - setting copy (3 folders)
      Page proofs (2 folders)
  - Ephemera
    - "The Low-Down on Tuberculosis" / by Arna Bontemps, undated; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
    - "Only Half a Life" / by Arna Bontemps (Evanston, Ill.: National WCTU Publishing House, 1947?)), Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - Monographs
    - American Missionary Association Archives in Fisk University Library / by Arna Bontemps (Nashville: s.n., 1947), Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - Music scores
    - "Golgotha Is a Mountain" Poem by Arna Bontemps; music by John W. Work (New York: Galaxy Music Corporation, 1959), Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
    - "Meine dunklen Hande: funf Negergedichte von Langston Hughes und Arna Bontemps" / Hermann Reutter (Mainz: B. Schott), undated; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
    - "Oh! I've Seen Many Mountains" Poem by Arna Bontemps; music by John W. Work (New York: Ethel Smith Music Corp., 1954), 2 copies; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
    - "Songs of Separation" / by William Grant Still (New York: Leeds Music Corporation, 1949) Includes selection "Idolatry" from poem by Arna Bontemps., Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
    - "St. Louis Woman" (New York: A-M Music Corporation, 1946), Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
      "Any Place I Hang My Hat is Home"
      "Cakewalk Your Lady"
      "I Wonder What Became of Me"
  - Playscripts
    - "Black Thunder", typescript manuscript fragment (Box 59)
    - "Careless Love", See "When the Jack Hollers".
    - "Cavalcade of the Negro Theatre", See "Jubilee".
    - "Les Cenelles", research notes; typescript manuscript; 4 folders (Box 59)
      R
    - "Creole Square" [with Schuyler Watts], typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 59)
    - "The Domino Mask" (alternate title: "The Quadroon Ball"), typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 59)
    - "The Great Speckled Bird" [with Jack Conroy], typescript manuscripts; 4 folders (Box 59)
    - "Honey Child", typescript manuscript (Box 59)
    - "Jubilee" [with Langston Hughes] (Box 59, 60)
    - "St. Louis Woman" [with Countee Cullen], typescript manuscripts; 9 folders (Box 60)
    - "The Sparrow's House" (alternate title: "Keepers of the House"), typescript manuscript (Box 60)
    - "When the Jack Hollers" [with Langston Hughes], typescript manuscripts; 4 folders (Box 61)
  - Poetry
    - [Miscellaneous], lists and tear sheets (Box 61)
  - Radio and television scripts
    - "Know Your Authors" (WCFL Chicago), 1939 May 6 (Box 61)
    - "Off the Bookshelf" (WJJD Chicago), 1940 June 25 (Box 61)
    - "Sad-Faced Boy" (CBS American School of the Air adaptation), 1940 Nov 28 (Box 61)
    - "Salute to Freedom" (CBS broadcast featuring an Arna Bontemps/Langston Hughes collaboration on "a radio poem on American folk heroes"), 1941 Dec. 14 (Box 61)
    - "Books That Live" (WJW Cleveland), 1955 Nov. 12 (Box 61)
    - "Saturday Night Theatre" intermission feature (WTMJ-TV), 1963 Apr. 20 (Box 61)
    - "Critique" (WMVS-TV Milwaukee), 1963 Apr. 22 (Box 61)
    - "Planet Earth", 1966 May 23 (Box 61)
    - [no title] (WDCN-TV on Jubilee Singers) - "What Can I Do?" (WBBM Chicago), 1966 June 16 (Box 61)
  - Song lyrics
    These were written, in part, in collaboration with Langston Hughes [et al.] for the 1940 Negro Exposition, Chicago, Ill.
    - "Boulevard Cowboy" (Box 61)
    - "Chocolate Carmencita" (Box 61)
    - "If You No Savvy I'll Make You Savvy Somehow" (Box 61)
    - "Jubilee - Jubilee" (Box 61)
    - "Little Flower of the Tropics" (Box 61)
    - "Lonely Little Maiden by the Sea" (Box 61)
    - "Market Day in Martinique" (Box 61)
    - "Rhythm Club Fire" (Box 61)
    - "Sweet Nothings in Spanish" (Box 61)
    - "That's the Way We Do It in Chicago" (Box 61)
    - "Voodoo Man" (Box 61)
    - "When the Sun Goes Down in Rhumba Land" (Box 61)
  - Speeches
    - "Adventures in Authorship", notes (Box 61)
    - "American Negro Poetry", typescript manuscript (Box 61)
    - "The Black Renaissance of the 1920's known as the Harlem Renaissance", typescript manuscript (Box 61)
    - "Black Writing Today", typescript manuscript (Box 61)
    - "Booker T. Washington", typescript manuscript (Box 61)
    - "The Breaking Patterns of Segregation", notes (Box 61)
    - Commencement address at Hampton High School (Dickson, Tenn.), 1959 (Box 61)
    - "Forgotten Men of the Negro Press", typescript manuscripts (Box 61)
    - "4 Freedoms", notes (Box 61)
    - "Four Lies", notes (Box 61)
    - "Freedom Is a Powerful Word", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Great Readers Make Great Writers", notes (Box 62)
    - "The Harlem Renaissance", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Hold Fast to Dreams", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Intro"[duction] for Charles S. Johnson, Fall 1948; typescript notes (Box 62)
    - "Introduction for Peter Abrahams", typescript manuscript (Box 62)
    - "The Literature of Freedom", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "The Lonesome Boy Theme", typescript manuscript (Box 62)
    - "Marian Anderson: an Introduction", notes, typescript manuscript (Box 62)
    - "The Meaning of Louis Armstrong: a public lecture on 'The Negro Contribution to American Culture'", notes (Box 62)
    - "Negro in American Culture", notes (Box 62)
    - "The Negro in Poetry & Drama", notes (Box 62)
    - "The Negro Renaissance: Jean Toomer and the Harlem Writers of the 1920's", typescript manuscript (Box 62)
    - "The Negro's Contribution Reconsidered", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Old Myths, New Negroes", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Opportunities for Development of Negro Talent", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Oration for Carl Van Vechten", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "The Poetry of the American Negro", notes (Box 62)
    - "The Poetry of the Negro", notes (Box 62)
    - "Public Oration for Paul E. Magloire", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Reading and the College Student", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Reading for Personal Development", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Recent Writing by Negroes", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "The Relevance of Dunbar", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "Remarks... [at] Student Convocation, Fisk, 1-4-'62" (re: literary contest), 1962 (Box 62)
    - "Remarks... in Presenting American Library Association's Liberty and Justice Book Award in Imaginative Literature to James Thurber for Further Fables for Our Time", Apr. 25, 1957; typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "A Renaissance Remembered", Apr. 14, 1962; address delivered at the 26th Annual Educational Conference of the Teachers Union of the City of New York; typescript manuscripts, two versions (Box 62)
    - "Significance of Charles S. Johnson Papers", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "A Statement... on Receiving Jane Addams Children's Book Award", 1956; manuscript fragment (Box 162)
    - "Three Negro Leaders", notes (Box 62)
    - "Why Negro History Week?", notes (Box 62)
    - "Words Like Freedom", typescript manuscripts (Box 62)
    - "The Writer's Window", notes (Box 62)
    - Untitled, A-Z by topic
      - Books and libraries, notes and holograph manuscript (Box 62)
      - Langston Hughes and the Harlem Renaissance, notes (Box 62)
      - Librarianship and authorship, notes (Box 62)
      - New Criticism and the African-American writer, notes (Box 62)
      - On presentation of a book to the Detroit Public Library, notes (Box 62)
      - Origins of African-American folklore, notes (Box 62)
      - Poetry and the modern world, notes (Box 62)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes (Box 62)
  - Stories
    - "Aunt Viney's Confession", holograph manuscript (Box 63)
    - "The Avengers", manuscript notes (Box 63)
    - "Barrel Staves," New Challenge, Mar. 1934; photocopy (Box 63)
    - "Big Six", holograph manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Boy Blue", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Cunning", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "The Cure", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Death at Heaven's Gate", holograph, typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "The Devil Is a Conjurer", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Don't Mind We Sisters", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Evil Woman", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Fast Sooner Hound" (excerpt), Children's Digest, Sept. 1952 (Box 63)
    - "A Feather for Calcedonia", holograph, typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Hair-trigger Kid", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Heathen at Home", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Hoppergrass Man", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Last Tag", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Let the Church Roll On", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Lonesome Boy, Silver Trumpet", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Saturday Night", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "A Summer Tragedy," Opportunity, June 1933; typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Talk to the Music" (working title: "The Blues She Sang"), typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "3 Pennies for Luck", typescript manuscript; 2 folders (Box 63)
      See also Writings: Articles and essays
    - "Voodoo Killing in Marksville", manuscript notes (Box 63)
    - "The Vultures", holograph manuscript (Box 63)
    - "Where Willie Went", holograph manuscript (fragment) (Box 63)
    - "Winter Night in the Summer House", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - "A Woman with a Mission", typescript manuscript (Box 63)
    - Untitled, A-Z by first line
      - "It must have been a matinee" (Box 63)
      - "It was about the most disrespectfullest thing... ." (Box 63)
    - Manuscript notes and plot outlines (Box 63)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Adah" [synopsis for a biographical novel about Adah Isaacs Menken], typescript manuscript, research material (Box 64)
    - "American Original" [essay collection], typescript manuscripts (Box 64)
    - "Bon-Bon Buddy" [juvenile, with Langston Hughes], typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 64)
    - "The Boy of the Border" [juvenile, with Langston Hughes], typescript manuscripts; 5 folders (Box 64)
    - "The Chariot in the Cloud" [novel], typescript manuscripts; 3 folders (Box 64)
    - Exhibitions:
      - 1940: American Negro Exposition (Chicago), captions, legends, titles (Box 64)
      - 1967: National Negro History Week observance, suggested guidelines (Box 64)
    - "The Free and the Fatherless", combined biography project on Frederick Douglass, Booker T. Washington, and W. E. B. Du Bois
      - Prospectus
      - Frederick Douglass section (published, in part, as Free at Last and 100 Years of Negro Freedom), research notes; typescript manuscripts; 8 folders (Box 64)
      - Booker T. Washington section (published, in part, as Young Booker and 100 Years of Negro Freedom) (Box 66, 67, 68, 69)
        Research notes (19 folders)
      - W. E. B. Du Bois section (published, in part, as 100 Years of Negro Freedom): (Box 69, 70, 71)
        Research notes (13 folders)
    - "God's Country: the Negro Comes to Illinois" [WPA project edited with Jack Conroy, later re-worked and, in part, published as They Seek a City], 10 folders (Box 71, 72)
      Research material
      Synopsis
    - "The Negro in Illinois", See "God's Country: the Negro Comes to Illinois".
    - "New Africa Series", introductory description for proposed Hill and Wang, Inc. series (Box 72)
    - "Of Many Waters" (working titles: "The Blue Battalion"; "The Gaudy Island") [novel], research notes; synopses; typescripts; 8 folders (Box 73)
    - "Paul Antoine" [play, with Langston Hughes], working notes, synopsis (Box 73)
    - "The Prizefighter and the Woman" [novel], notes; holograph manuscript (notebook); typescript manuscript (Box 73, 74)
    - "Rat Tales" (working title: "Waterfront Streets") [anthology], research material; 2 folders (Box 74)
    - "Sugar Hill" [anthology], typescript manuscripts; 2 folders (Box 74)